so Nancy asked me she keeps sending me
emails what are you going to teach in
New York at the three Jews in the
afternoon and I'm like I have no
idea uh but then uh we're doing a
program uh with uh pure yoga and with
shivananda Yoga Center in New York and
Bahamas and um me and the Swami down
there Swami Banda who's a very wonderful
teacher so I've been going there for I
don't know since 1999 I think uh and
teaching maybe once a year down there
and we are frankly quite different
philosophies and uh but I think we are
very proud of of the
collaboration uh because we are
different traditions we are
hardcore followers of our own traditions
and we love to be with each other and we
compare notes and you know it's really
beautiful so it's like a something that
started over a thousand years ago and
we're picking it up we are distant
cousins uh our yoga tradition niguma and
naropa came from West Bengal and so did
their tradition probably we were
practicing together a thousand years ago
so we we were talking like what can we
do together what kind of program could
we do together and we decided to call it
Nirvana immersion and the idea is uh you
know Nirvana is defined as uh who
knows this is this is her moment of do
it
again so means your negative emotions
jealousy
anger uh desire for
Pringles uh okay and then uh malupa
means all of them uh banga means get rid
of them forever so Tang means because
you saw Ultimate Reality in a deep state
of meditation you saw Ultimate Reality
that's a definition of nirvana okay so
it's possible to achieve Nirvana this
afternoon and you don't look different
to other people except you probably
never you're never grumpy uh it's not
Enlightenment it's not full buddhahood
okay Nirvana comes long before that
and uh Nirvana is when you achieve the
ability never to get upset again no one
can upset you again ever and you are
never jealous of anyone again and like
God all your negativities are forever
you're not even thinking about your old
boyfriend
anymore okay like you are Beyond that's
Nirvana okay and uh that can be uh
anytime in your life you can achieve
Nana it's not the same as Enlightenment
okay Enlightenment comes later in
Enlightenment you expand further and you
are able for example to see all events
on all worlds in the universe at the
same time past present and future all
things which have ever been all things
which ever shall be and all things that
are now uh you are able to proceed in
the same moment every moment of your
life okay and then you serve on those
planets in countless
body
uh nice uh maybe
him her
her
uh so I thought you know we're going to
do a six day program on Nirvana and I
really like it uh the the scriptures are
very rich in teachings on Nirvana it's
very very moving very beautiful so I've
been working hard on those and there's
about I don't know
100 pages of new translations and and
writings on Nirvana and we'll be doing
that three nights in New York Friday
we'll fly down to the Bahamas and
continue it down there in a more
congenial
atmosphere they have a nice Beach and uh
so anyway that's the plan three days
here three days there we pick out
your most outstanding negative emotion
and we work on that for a week okay mine
is jealousy okay I can tell tell uh I'm
very good at it and uh so you pick your
main negativity each person picks their
own and then you there are as practices
aimed at that and there are meditations
aimed at that and then there are
teachings name that that for a week so
the theory is that in a week you would
at least get to know how bad it is you
know
and no Nirvana if you can it's like a
gang fight we used to have small gang
fights when I grew up
not not big ones okay but in a gang
fight you always go for the the biggest
guy on the other side you go for the
leader first then if you knock him out
the rest of people just run away so uh
that's the idea with Nirvana you go for
your
worst emotion and you knock that out and
then the rest kind of collaps after that
okay so that's what we're working on but
then I I realized it occurred to me that
we would never get to enlightenment in
that program we we won't be talking
about what it's like to become a Buddha
we're just talking about Nana right
which is long before you become a Buddha
so I thought
um finally I got this inspiration I woke
up you know and uh llama gave me an
inspiration and I thought
um let's talk about Enlightenment at the
threejs you know like what happens later
after Nirvana okay so this is for next
Monday uh Enlightenment because up till
then you're just doing your okay uh so
uh I'm going to talk about uh
Enlightenment with you and I thought uh
nowadays I'm in this mood in my old age
that um what I teach should be relevant
to people's lives uh so uh I thought uh
let's go
through what you will be like when you
get enlightened okay cuz people ask me
it's kind of weird to think about right
like will I have long
ears uh do will I have a big belly and a
bald head you know uh yeah right Paul I
mean we it when you get
closer it starts to happen just to the
special people um but
uhal
terms uh if if I could become a Buddha
by next year right then what would that
mean if as far as my trips to Starbucks
and relationships and you know things I
enjoy doing can I still go to SAR
Academy and do the courses there or do I
have to stop you know like I think we
don't think about it much you know and
uh I thought it would be nice to go
through what it's like and uh you can
draw these descriptions from two sources
right one is
scripture right the the qualities of a
Buddha are
so beyond everything that you kind of
have to go to scripture and ask what
what's it going to be like when I get
there
right then but you can also draw
from encounters uh with enlightened
beings and uh those are occur first
during uh deep deep meditation okay so
in deep
meditations uh particularly on emptiness
you can make contact with enlightened
beings uh up until that moment of the
first
direct communion with Ultimate Reality
are you a Buddhist you say yes I'm a
Buddhist and then you say have you ever
met a Buddha and you say no and has
there ever been a Buddha yes there was
gatama 2 and a half thousand years ago
uh but you can't confirm much right you
can't say I met one and this is what
they're like giraffe you can say I went
to the zoo there was a
giraffe it does have a long neck it has
spots you know what I mean but Buddha is
hard you know I'm a Buddhist but I've
never confirmed the existence of Buddhas
you see directly I've never had direct
communication or encounter with a Buddha
so all that we know about Buddhas is is
here say it's
reports about Buddhas and over two half
thousand years reports can get corrupted
right we can do that game where I tell
Michael something and then he whispers
it to the next person and it goes around
the room and then by the time it gets to
the last person it's pretty weird it's
completely different right this happens
in my real life you know a lot uh
so there's reports about what Buddhists
are like and those I'm going to teach
you today the from the most authentic
scripture then you know but by necessity
even in the Buddhist tradition which is
extraordinarily careful things can get
corrupted you know or they can
get if you pass on you're talking uh 75
Generations right uh if for 75
Generations you pass on something
without having met them without having
met a Buddha then that information can
be a little academic or something okay
and then you've got to go into states of
deep meditation you have to learn how to
meditate come to the three
Jews uh learn how to meditate uh or to
the classes in other parts of New York
and then uh at some point if you're
careful and if you're well trained and
if you're devoted you will have direct
experiences of of enlightened beings and
then then you can see the scriptures are
generally correct but but not as it cool
okay all right so uh so we will draw
from both sources okay uh about today
okay so let's get started does does
anybody not have a reading raise your
hand are there more
no okay all right we sure
uh so the title of this talk is me as
Buddha what will I be like the
advertisement said will I still wear
jeans and will they still fit you
know those are important
questions uh then I thought the first
verse would be nice I'll say it in
tibetan because it's a
blessing very famous okay these are
the words of praise to an angel called
vaj yogini okay uh a diamond the angel
of
diamond uh in light who is a Buddha
right one kind of Buddha and then these
are words of praise to that Buddha very
famous uh a lot of people in this in our
immediate lineage are practicing her
Tantra and these are famous words in
Praise of her
and they say I bow down to The Shining
angel of diamond Empress of angels who
has the five wisdoms who has the three
bodies who protects all living beings
okay so I bow down to that lady in
lighted woman
okay I pulled out this verse
because uh it describes an enlightened
being okay and it it contains the main
elements what going to be like when you
become a Buddha you will have the five
wisdoms and you will have the three
bodies okay then I thought if if I had
to describe Enlightenment in an hour or
two or what you're going to be like when
you become a Buddha I thought it would
be nice to take off from this verse okay
so physically or you will have three
bodies and then you will have five kinds
of wisdom okay in your mind this is what
your body and mind look like when you
get enlightened okay so then we'll just
go straight into some ancient sources
about what are those bodies and what are
those wisdoms okay the bodies of a
Buddha can be taught as three or four
okay uh there's an old tradition of
three bodies and then uh it has become a
tradition in recent years which means
since 350
ad uh for uh describing it as four
bodies they split one of the three into
two and they come up with four bodies so
sometimes you'll hear the two bodies of
a Buddha physical and mental you'll hear
the three bodies of a Buddha and then
sometimes you'll hear the four bodies of
a Buddha so the verse to vaj yogini was
talking about three bodies but we're
going to split one of them into two and
we'll come out with four bodies I think
it's good if you learn it as four then
you can abbreviate it if you don't have
time someday when you're teaching it to
two or three okay but we have time all
right so the first one is the Essence
body
uh let me
see
[Music]
sayik okay this is the Essence body the
first of the four bodies traditionally
in the Essence body is taught first okay
this gets into Buddha nature okay this
has to do with Buddha nature let talk
about that and then we can go to to more
y the Essence
body so it is said in the scriptures
that all of us are a Buddha at heart
okay we are enlightened already okay
there is a part about us which is
already a Buddha okay by the way I mean
it it goes without saying that one of
the cool things about Buddhism is that
you get to be God
eventually okay I mean if you said that
in my church when I was growing up it
would be a no no you know uh but in
Buddhism I think it's very beautiful to
point out that the goal of Buddhism is
that each person uh will become a Buddha
it's it's inevitable you will you all of
us will become a Buddha those of you who
are not and I don't know who who uh I'm
not yet so but everybody will be that's
just the basic principle of Buddhism you
know a Buddhist practice imagine a
Christian practice where you are meant
to become Jesus not to be with Jesus or
not to be with God in heaven or
something like that the point of
Buddhism is that you
become uh Buddha and it's almost as if
you would become Jesus or become God or
become Moses or something like that
Muhammad okay the goal of Buddhism is
that you become a Buddha that's possible
because you already have one part of
what you will be it's already part of
you okay that's cool all right it's
hardwired into you uh you already have a
part of you which is enlightened okay uh
and that's your Essence body
luku uh and sometimes they call sugat
Gara which means uh Buddha nature right
the Buddha seed that you have so what is
that like okay because that's what makes
it possible for you to become God or
Jesus or Buddha okay uh what is it about
you that you already have which is
already enlightened okay and and there's
a lot of arguments about that and a lot
of wrong ideas about that um but it's
like this okay uh you
ready what's going to
happen yeah yeah you ready here it comes
okay one two
three
uh I'm not going to do the whole pen
thing cuz you'll fall asleep the people
in DCI are conditioned to fall asleep
when I go like
that uh so
uh
uh when I when I went like that okay
when I pulled it out I just pulled out a
black stick okay cylinder it's a black
cylinder in the moment that my hand
went from not visible to you to visible
to you in that moment a karmic seed
broke open in your mind okay a karmic
seed broke open in your subconscious all
right and out of that seed popped a
small picture made of light uh it's just
a what do you call it it's like a what
are those they put on bars the writing
in uh NE neon neon it's like neon okay
it is is self Illuminating okay a karmic
seed breaks open and a self-illuminating
image pops out okay it's about that big
okay the pen image in your mind is about
that big if you ever became aware of it
in a deep meditation it would feel about
that big okay uh it's a perfect little
picture of a
pen then your mind
uh your mind is looking at
image and it's overlaid on this thing
you see what I mean like uh what do you
call that transparency the overhead
transparency it the pen thing is laid
upon this
object in the millisecond that I pull it
out in that much time a karmic seat has
opened in your mind okay there is no
your eye cannot see a
pen the eye can only the rods and cones
of the what you call that
retina can only detect colors and shapes
they're not capable of making a judgment
call about what that object is okay
that's done by the Mind by the intellect
the the eye can only detect black C
cylindrical it's a black cylindrical who
made it a pen is coming from your mind
okay why did you choose a pen and not
a right white or both okay I like to Che
on that uh
is that you have the kic seed to see of
P
okay you have the seed in your mind who
put the seed there only you no one else
can put a seed in your mind okay only
you can put a seed in your mind and you
can only put it in your mind by
interacting with another person okay
karmic seeds the planting of a karmic
seed depends on somebody else okay if
you want to plant a seed for a pen
you're going to have to plant it with
somebody else if you want to plant a
seed for a partner you're going to have
to plant it with somebody else you can't
plant a kic seed without another person
not can't do it okay only you can plant
what's in your mind but you can only
plant it by helping another person okay
if you want a partner you have
to help a lonely person somewhere okay
if if you want pens you have to share
pens if you want money you have to help
other people make money okay that's just
where these things come from and that's
cool right then you can design your
life okay that's kind of once you
understand the system you can design how
your life goes right so I see a pen but
a dog season something to chew on right
and it's coming from my mind the karmic
seed has opened and cracked open and and
the image is coming out of my mind this
and this are the same okay this this
cylinder flesh colored cylinder and this
black cylinder are the same okay they
are both my perception of this is coming
from me okay there are
seeds opening in my mind 65 per second
are opening in my mind and making me see
a human arm of Flesh and Blood okay
that's just the way it is question for
you if I take this thing and I leave it
here and there's all the people go out
of the room and all the dogs go out of
the room then at that
moment is at that time while everybody's
gone and it's sitting on this chair
alone is it a pen or is it a
choy neither you can't say neither I
like people all over the world I ask
this question and everybody goes like
that okay that's sh okay that's
emptiness all right and nothing
else okay it doesn't mean black black
close your eyes everything's black press
hard you see green
dots you're close to seeing in emptiness
you know and uh it doesn't mean stare at
the wall and see thoughts float through
your mind it doesn't mean any of it
doesn't mean everything's an allergic
it doesn't matter whether you kick me or
kiss me uh those are all dumb they don't
help you okay what emptiness means is by
itself when there's nobody around having
karmic seeds pop open in their mind this
pen is like a a white blank screen I
realized a few weeks ago that blank
probably comes from
Blanc right and uh it's a white screen
it's it's a blank Blan white screen and
uh where in it becomes a pen if the dog
walks in it becomes a too by itself
which one then you got to go like that
everybody go like that it's good yoga
exercise if you're from India you can
fudge
it
uh but
uh I'm also like that you see my body is
also like that right
I have uh certain seeds in my mind they
are breaking open as I speak 65 per
second and they are making me see this
as a as an arm of Flesh and Blood which
is sort of like better than being on
fire but worse than being made of light
I'm sort of somewhere in the middle of
the range of possible
existences okay I'm not in a Hell realm
and I'm not a Buddha I see an arm of
flesh and blood from the point of view
of the hell realm it's it's good luck
from the point of view of the arm of
light I still have some ways to go right
but I my seeds are making me see an arm
of Flesh and Blood
right but that that cylinder is blank
and is a white blank screen right it
also has its own emptiness okay I could
be seeing what is that I could be having
a
V8 uh I could be seeing something else
if I had planted better seeds in my mind
okay I could be seeing an arm of light
like The Shining Empress of angels okay
I could be seeing an arm of
Light by itself this cylinder is only a
blank white screen I'm available to
become made of light okay I'm available
for that I'm open for that I'm a blank
white screen okay that part of me is a
Buddha already
got it that part of me will be the same
when I become enlightened and that's the
only part of me that will be the same
when I become enlightened got it you
already enlightened the most important
part of an enlightened being you already
have it's the fact that you are a blank
white screen you are available for
yourself to see as a Buddha now already
and you always have been okay you're
also available to see yourself as a do
okay you got to be
careful okay you are a blank white
screen you have an emptiness that's your
Essence body that's your sugat garma
that's your Buddha nature it's very
beautiful you already have the raw
material to be a Buddha you already
enlightened part of you is already
enlightened okay because you are coming
from your mind you are available to be
something else if you just plan
different con seeds there's room for
them to do their thing and that's that's
your Essence body and you already have
it okay it's very
beautiful and that's your Buddha nature
okay it's nothing else there's not like
a little seed in you that's a Buddha or
something like like you have to do an
operation a heart operation somewhere
inside under the par par cardium there's
a Buddha or something that's that's all
dumb okay
you
you you're empty you are a blank white
screen and so you're already enlightened
from that point that part of you is
already enlightened
okay um that's your Essence body now
traditionally they divide that body into
two parts okay
uh and I forget uh it's
here
means
there's an emptiness hanging off of
every object in this room okay you got
to get used to that how many emptinesses
in this
room as many as there are objects as
many as there are objects or parts of
objects it gets a little it gets a
little weird okay like one hair on my
head has thousands of emptinesses the
tip has its own emptiness the the next
part has its own emptiness okay
what's that
mean every object in this room is like a
blank white movie screen and could turn
into anything else if I had the
seats okay that's the emptiness of every
object in this room okay every every
person in this room could be divine if I
had the right seats I would see you as
Divine
okay so everything has its
own
emptiness empty ESS is hanging off of
everything in the world all right now
those emptinesses are divided into two
okay the kind that are hanging off
of things already all the time okay like
every object has its own emptiness right
pure
emptiness but the thing it's hanging off
of could be Pure or not okay okay the
budd's emptinesses The Emptiness of a
Buddha's hair is hanging off of
something which is pure okay yeah yeah
yeah by the way you can hang emptiness
on emptiness but that gets a little
touchy it's true but that's don't go
there your head will
explode
uh so emptiness can be hanging off
something which is pure or something
which is not yet Pure or something which
was impure and is now pure okay okay so
the Essence body of a Buddha is divided
into two kinds one is the part which has
always been pure which is which is the
emptiness that you already have you
already
have the the pure by Nature brutal body
is already part of you okay
but the emptiness of a Buddha of the
parts of a Buddha which used to be
impure and are now pure we don't have
that one got it we we are impure we are
mortal and we are limited to the present
moment right our knowledge is limited to
the present moment we are
impure if we practice hard we will
become pure okay our our physical body
will change and our mental being will
change and they will become totally pure
The Emptiness of those things which were
impure and are now pure is half of the
Essence body and we don't have that one
yet okay we don't have the emptiness of
the things that used to be impure and
are now pure
okay sometimes you can call it the
absence of the
impurity okay which is technically not
emptiness all right those of you who
care okay anyway to summarize the first
of the four bodies just cuz we don't
have 3 weeks to talk about it
um there's a piece of you which is
already enlightened and will not change
and that's the fact that you are
available to be anything if you have
differ seeds okay there's a part of you
which is available to be anything and
that you're going to carry all the way
to Enlightenment that part of you will
not
change and that's your that's the reason
you will become enlightened it's it's
inevitable okay because you have that
sin in you you have that emptiness you
must become a Buddha in in time every
living creature from amibas to humans
right every ant every burn every Mouse
will be every whale will become an
enlightened being it's
inevitable okay that's your Essence body
so I like that one like if you die in
the middle of the class at least you
heard that one
okay somebody told you you're already
part of Buddha part Buddha and proved it
to you okay right it's the same okay uh
you have that body already and it's very
beautiful okay you are already partly
Divine okay and
that's that's the reason you must become
Divine eventually okay if you PR
eventually all beings change okay I
that's one of my favorite things about
Buddhism okay all right right body
number two page two at the bottom I'm
I'm quoting different llamas
okay I pulled out chony Lama who's from
the
1600s uh and went to the greatest
Monastery in the
world which is Sarah may not
Jay uh the half of Sarah that I went to
uh he he wrote the textbook for for our
Monastery in the
1600s okay late 1600s Master K dead is
the other textbook writer from s he
lived in the 1500s okay he I I selected
a piece from him for the wisdom body
this is all in the car coming back from
Princeton yesterday at midnight okay but
it's
beautiful that's because we have the
database of 1 million Pages typed in by
Tibetan refugees this year is the 25th
anniversary of that Pro
Mark tret is working very hard on that
G's working very hard on that where are
you Mark went to go meet with another
organization that's working on it but
it's only possible that you can have
these things because of their work and
we should have a big party in New York
like in the fall or something we should
have a big reception 25th anniversary
okay probably they'll just give you some
cheap Apple sparkly stuff and hit you up
from
donation uh
okay uh when you become a Buddha you
will have a wisdom bnny it is the
ultimate
wisdom uh where all impure nature of
your mind has transformed into a pure
nature then there are 21 groups of
qualities I'm not going to go over them
with you cuz we don't have
time
now
uh first paragraph on page three listen
to me before you read it okay because
you'll get a headache
um this is the body they split to get
four okay they split the wisdom body off
from the Essence body right technically
the Essence body is the emptiness of all
the forms of wisdom that the Buddha has
got
it uh so they
chose to split off the
emptinesses from the wisdoms that a
[Music]
has
and and lump all those wisdoms together
and call them the wisdom body okay Dak
okay uh and you
ready they
split the mind of a Buddha from the
emptiness of that mind you already
possess that emptiness okay but you
don't possess that mind the omnicient
mind so try to imagine what that mind is
like Okay um
well we're going to get there
later right now we are confined to the
present moment you don't think it's so
bad because you never saw anything else
you've lived in a closet your whole life
and you like it you
know I can move around and I got three
coats in
here has a nice
feeling uh you know I got a knob on the
door
you know uh no you've never experienced
anything else your mind has the
capacity to not be limited to the
present moment okay the present moment
only lasts for 165th of a fingers now
you are confined you are in prison in
the present moment you don't get to be
in the future in the present moment and
you don't get to be in all the past time
that has ever been in the present moment
but when you become a Buddha that
limitation is dropped okay and it's cool
it's really cool then we have another
limitation even if you could expand
my presence in time to 5 minutes long if
I could be downstairs mentally getting
out of the car and be here at the same
time you couldn't handle it you would
people would call you crazy or Autistic
or something see I mean you you if you
really could perceive all the moments
from the time you got out of the car
until the time you got here it would be
confusing okay you you'd be unsure where
where you were so one of the cool things
about a Buddha's mind is that you are
able to
organize uh all past time and all future
time and be completely present in each
moment at the same time that's
cool okay you can Witness this Lincoln's
assassination and then you can see
yourself becoming Miss America on planet
23 uh 10 billion years from now you've
been Miss America countless times even
the
guys okay uh and you will be again
countless times and uh you can enjoy
them all at the same time the moment
when they open the thing and you're like
and you know uh you know
a Buddha can experience all of them at
the same time and not get confused okay
that's maybe it's lucky we're limited to
the present moment some of us have
trouble even being there
right uh so anyway that limitation drops
I I don't know how to describe it to you
but try to imagine okay it h when you uh
see emptiness directly and when you
first have a direct experience
OFA for a short time maybe 10 minutes
you will have an experience similar to
that and you are capable of
seeing countless beings at the same time
okay for 10 minutes in your meditation
after you see emptiness directly when
you come out of that you're able to see
the faces of countless beings at the
same time okay and that's that
experience once you've had it you are
changed forever you can never be the
same and your priorities can never be
the same right you're talking countless
planets and you know that you will take
care of them at part of the experience
is you know that you will take care of
them those planets and each of those
beings and you see them all at the same
moment you see the faces of every living
being animals Birds
fish you know amibas humans Gods you see
them all in the same moment okay your
mind has this capacity when you become
enlightened that becomes a permanent
State you are that way all the time okay
it's try to imagine what your priorities
would be if that ever happened to you
for five minutes you know could you
worry about not getting your latte in
the
morning uh if you knew you had an
appointment on a billion
planets you know
shortly okay like that's a huge blessing
to have that experience if you come to
the three jewels I'm doing a sales job
if you learn to meditate really you can
have that I you can have that experience
sitting in this room where you are now
that can happen to you if you play your
cards
right right come make it a regular
practice do your meditation regularly
quietly modestly no big fuss just come
do your
meditation uh that will happen to you
and then and then your life has some
kind of special meaning right so anyway
your mind has that
capacity why why sometimes they sayana
Daka right they mix the wisdom of a
Buddha with the emptiness of that mind
what's the emptiness of the mind
mean uh I can go like this and say my
arm is the same as the pen but I can
also go like this and say my brain is
the same as the pen okay the way you
experience your own mind is coming from
little
pictures popping out of little seeds
that were planted in your mind by you
last week or last month I was unkind to
someone who was sad they needed some
help I ignored them that planted seeds
in my mind those seats are opening this
week I feel
depressed you are not thinking the
depression you're listening to it you're
a witness right are you the thinker of
the thoughts and in your mind or are you
the person listening cuz you can't be
both at the same time
right uh you're you're actually a what
do you call victim/witness
you don't have a choice you have to hear
what seeds open in your mind you know
Mike Michael wig are you
here yeah I he used to go up to see Ken
ruche our teacher right and I used to go
up to try to translate or or take them
tea or something he used to come like
once a month wants to see our llama and
I remember one day uh Ken R was yelling
at him and Michael was having some
personal crisis about something I don't
remember what it was and probably about
where to park your car or something and
uh rtin was yelling at him and saying
just be happy just be happy you know and
then Michael laughed and and then I went
upstairs and I said R you know what kind
of advice is that you know like tell
somebody just be happy if they could be
happy they wouldn't come to have an
appointment with you you
know and uh because you're only
listening to what what seeds are popping
open in your mind you don't have a
choice it depends on how you treated
people last week is what you will hear
your mind being your mind is also empty
your mind is also blank and uh you will
experience your mind in in exact
accordance to the seeds that you have
planted with other people if you've been
kind to people who were sad or depressed
then you will hear happy thoughts and if
you haven't been you will hear depressed
thoughts okay so that's also coming from
you so you have your
mind that you're listening to as seeds
open and then you have the empty
emptiness of that mind the blank white
cleanness of your mind okay got
it uh sometimes those two for Buddha are
Lum together they're state of mind which
is knowing all things and then the
emptiness of that state of mind which is
that they used to be not a Buddha and
now they're a Buddha and they collected
enough seeds that they get to see their
mind as being a Buddhist mind got it the
closet mind went to the billion planets
mind all right did it change no did the
seeds change yes the mind is the same
same mind okay same thing right pen or
Choy same is the Mind human mind closet
mine or or billion Planet mine it just
depends on what seeds you have
okay so in our tradition uh for the last
I don't know 17 centuries we have split
those two into two the mind of a Buddha
the mental state of a Buddha and The
Emptiness of that mind The Emptiness is
part of the Essence body and then the
wisdom body is the mind of a Buddha so
so far we have two of the three big
parts of any creature there's your
physical body
there's your state of mind and there's
the blank white screen that lies behind
both of them okay you have your blank
white screen this that lets you be
anything then you have your mental part
and then you have your physical part we
have finished this blank white
screenless part with which
Body Essence body and then we finish the
the mental part with the wisdom body so
now we can go on to the two physical
parts of a Buddha okay the top of Page
Three what he's trying the point he's
trying to make is that the wisdom of a
Buddha from the blank white screen of
that wisdom because the wisdom of a
Buddha produces the two physical bodies
of a Buddha got it it
triggers the two physical bodies of a
Buddha you get enlightened first a
millisecond later your mind sends out
Bodies Okay technically in the first
moment of Enlightenment you are
deficient you don't have a physical
Buddha body yet the mind the the wisdom
mind the mental state creates two bodies
within a millisecond after that okay so
the first millisecond is sort of dicey
it's a big subject of debate in the
monastery oh first millisecond of a
Buddha are they a Buddha yes do they are
they a full Buddha yes do they have all
the bodies of a Buddha
no you like that people love to argue
about that okay all night long it
doesn't go anywhere uh so
anyway in the first millisecond after
your mind becomes enlightened you start
getting bodies physical body different
kind of physical body here we go body
number three uh Tony
Lama when you become a Buddha you will
have a Paradise Body I'm on the second
half of Page Three
okay and it's called saying
okay it's it's defined as the physical
body of a Buddha which has five things
about it which are absolutely
certain it has I call it certainty just
cuz it sounds cool but when you become a
Buddha you will have a body physical
body that has five qualities that are
always the same so it's that that
physical form of a Buddha is defined as
the physical form of a buddhis has the
five qualities which are always the same
they're never different okay they are
fixed forever all Buddhist have those
five okay this is the body you hang out
in in your Paradise okay you have a
Buddha paradise and you hang out in that
body there okay then you have other
bodies that you send to planet Earth
Michael Wick bodies take care of the
fundraising Nancy Karen
bodies sent from Buddhas that are
hanging out somewhere else like a cosmic
Starbucks and then then they are sending
bodies here to pay the bills at three JS
so we can have this
talk uh so we're going to go through the
five certainties the five things that
you will definitely have when you get
that body the first of the two physical
bodies number one
it is certain to be adorned by the marks
and signs of the body of enlightened
beam and these will be perfectly
distinct okay uh there are 112 marks and
signs of an enlightened be okay I pulled
them out in case we had time to start
them but it's not going to happen but
maybe next time okay uh it's cool all
right for example if you look carefully
at a Buddha
image uh they will have have this little
dot here
right
uh and uh that's a that's a part of
their physical body only Buddhists have
it those weren't they weren't put on
those paintings but other cool things
were uh and uh this particular thing
it's weird okay there's a little hair
here that that grows on an enlightened
being and it can stretch to the end of
the
universe and it represents their ability
to to the end of the universe okay the
karma for that sign of an enlightened
being is helping your own personal
teacher get to where they need to
go okay isn't that interesting like like
R would say uh who wants to drive me to
the airport and there'd be like 100
people like I want I want to take you
you know we would fight over taking him
to the airport uh because then you get
this
theme uh so each and this allows you to
see the the needs of countless people
okay it's a special ability to see the
needs of countless people I want that so
you know you have to
like go on what's that cheap air tickets
or something what's the other one orbit
yeah for those of you who spend half
your life on orbit trying to find cheap
lights from Bahamas to
Moscow uh really that's a good uh CA
that okay don't feel sad it's going to
all have a result you might have to
shave it once in a
while been uh so there are all all all
beings who get enlightened have special
marks you have a dhma Wheels imprinted
on your
palms okay like that you have your body
is made of gold light like that they're
112 uh marks uh 32 and
80 uh they then
uh other beings in the world have
special Karma there's a thing called
Coro which means like the karma to be
elected president of the United States
Obama has the karma right now
right
uh in certain cases those people will
start to get this the the the wheel in
their hand they will start to get lines
on their Palm that suggest the wheel
right but they are not distinct and
they're not clear like Buddha has them
on the SES of their feet and the hand
and the palms of their hand clearly
imprint of a Dharma wheel right meaning
that they will teach so other beings
have them but not distinct so that's why
he wrote
here uh perfectly distinct okay
so if there's a Spoke missing you're not
there yet okay quality so it's definit
you will have those 112 qualities okay
physical qualities uh second the body is
certain to be surrounded by nothing less
than a or buus okay sorry to use
Sanskrit but it was easier Aya means in
in Sanskrit anyone who has seen
emptiness directly right is an Aya okay
then there are AAS who are not bodh saas
and there are AAS who are bodh saas okay
it's possible to see emptiness directly
and not have ultimate compassion okay I
think certain scientists might qualify
like that I I read a book from by a
scientist who said you never touch the
floor when you walk across the floor
you're never touching the floor you know
the electrons keep them apart and you
never really touch the floor and people
like that are close to having some kind
of breakthrough about emptiness but
they're not concerned about all the
people in the world right they're just
sort of into this mental space about hey
it's cool that you never step on the
floor so uh in this case we're talking
about a who are Buddhist saas okay they
saw emptiness directly and in the hours
following that experience when they came
out of that meditation while they were
still on their meditation cushion they
have that experience of seeing countless
beings and knowing that they will serve
them and that's body they they they
developed the direct experience of B CH
okay so we're talking about Aras who are
bodh satas and and once you get to be a
Buddha you never meet anybody
else okay you just have that Karma
nothing less he says nothing less
right uh yeah nothing less than an aaho
supp soft you hang out with special
people okay this gets me into another
subject okay this doesn't all happen in
five minutes okay this happens slowly
over thousands and thousands of Life
times right uh this happens slowly
throughout your body if you practice
Tantra it can happen in one
lifetime which is the point right of of
doing that
but but normally the process is very
slow and gradual what I'm saying is
slowly as your practice gets better as
your meditation gets better as your
study through the ACI courses taught by
Hector and John
progresses you will meet one special
person
you know and they will kind of hang out
with you and then another will come
right like two of the people you know
are special and then you meet another
person I was with where Sharon Cheryl
carstein I yeah okay we were joking
about how she got into the Dharma and I
remember this story we had a friend
named Tom Kylie who was uh he's the uh
irritating voice of the first few ACI uh
tapes
if you wanted to know but uh he was a
cab driver at the time and uh she got
into the back seat and he said where do
you want to go lady and she's like I
have to rush up town I'm late you know
and he's like well what are you going up
town for she says I'm going to hear the
DI Lama speak you know and then he turns
around and says you're going to hear the
Dil Lama speak and he said like yeah he
you should meet my llama can remember to
you know so that's how she got started
right so she had enough Karma to meet
this first person who was special you
see what I mean and as your spiritual
journey progresses as you meditate more
and more do more yoga study more you
will start
to attract spiritual people around you
okay actually you're not attracting them
they
are right your mind is changing the
season your mind is changing and the
Schmucks around you are turning into
tantric angel
okay all right got it you're making them
special and by the time the process is
finished you never get to meet anybody
else than an extraordinary spiritual
being okay it's cool it's cool so I
don't know in my own life I'm not like a
great practitioner I have lots of
failings weaknesses but I but I do I'm
starting to see this Karma develop you
know I'm surrounded by extraordinarily
wonderful people all the time you know
and I have people helping me with all my
projects I'm I have my two attendants
they are I have other people taking care
of all my things and I'm just surrounded
in this bubble of of beautiful people
and that will get better and better as
you practice okay you will start to meet
special people because you're creating
them and it will get hotter and hotter
and cooler and cooler until finally
you're in this Buddha paradise and you
never meet anybody who's not a a bodh
sappa in an area okay got it I like
that just understand that all these
things are going to happen gradually you
know one person will come and then two
people will come and then you meet five
people and then you'll be friends with
them and then you'll hang out together
you do yoga together and then it will
get better and better okay that's your
career path and it's Pleasant it's
called de de okay I think it's almost
more fun not to be a budha cuz you get
to have all this progress going on you
get to have more and more cool people
show up in your life then it gets out of
hand you know hundreds and thousands of
cool people you're like where were they
last year you
know okay it's a very nice thing to look
forward to okay if you practice
sincerely modestly quietly
humbly then
uh then you will be surrounded by cooler
and cooler people and that's in itself
is a reason to meditate you see
okay I'm almost there and I'm really
appreciative of that I appreciate all
the beautiful people around me you know
I'm very lucky that way
okay number three the body is certain to
remain without pretending to pass into
its final Nirvana until the last living
being has departed from the cycle of
pain okay so why they say
pretend is that a Buddha doesn't have to
die right the the Buddha who came to
this Planet 2 and half thousand years
ago uh we called they
say it's the Tibetan translation for
Nirvana we'll talk about it on tomorrow
night at pure
yoga but by the way you can drop in they
rob you but hey it's worth
it it's not
mine I'd rather do this kind of thing
but
anyway uh they're doing what I asked
them to do but you know
anyway uh I wanted them to for yoga I
wanted anyway I wanted people to make a
living but they're making a living
okay but I like the ones who don't make
a living better okay uh anyway both are
okay
anyway uh we'll talk about this one
tomorrow but uh so means to pretend to
to pretend to die or to pretend to leave
this world so in in tibetan for example
you don't say uh llama sh sh song you
don't say the Llama died especially
about your own teacher you say
Lama G Okay g say
G the llama's wishes were fulfilled for
the time
being okay they don't say that they
don't say l died so they say they left
this planet because it was the right
time or something like that which I
don't believe in but
anyway uh they shouldn't leave it all
right okay so that's go uh anyway this
body refuses to
disappear uh until the Lost being is
enlightened they promise to hang around
that's the fourth third quality of that
b that body will
stay in its Paradise until the last
being is enlightened and it will not
withdraws for from our experience
[Music]
yay okay that's lucky all right number
four we're on page
four this body is certain to utter only
teachings which belong to the system of
the greater way so this body is always
talking about emptiness this body is
always two do the people in that body's
direct Circle right the AR body surface
all they do is talk about
Mahayana they only talk about cool stuff
how can we save the world you know which
city do we have to go to next which
obscure City doesn't have dharm programs
yet you know they they talk about going
to Sophia or kia
or uh
duai like that
okay like that's all they do they hang
out and they talk about flights to weird
new cities how can we make this world
perfect okay they're just talking
Mahayana talk they have the vision
Mahana means they have a vision of a
world where there's no hunger and
there's no war and there's no poverty
and they're always blabbing about how to
pull that
off okay that's all they really want to
talk about sometimes they talk about
Ohio State football
games but uh it's all in the context of
enlightening the
world
[Music]
uh quality number five this body is
certain to reside only in the paradise
known as below no other it just
means uh you will never leave your
Paradise you will always live in your
Paradise okay where is the
paradise
where is the paradise where is your
Buddha Paradise it won't be a different
place okay Apollo will never find the
Budd Paradise okay no you think that
right part in your mind you think uh you
think sometimes other planet right
Buddha Paradise I mean your your child
mind takes over the when your parents
taught you about God when you were a kid
and you automatically assumed he was up
in the sky somewhere I don't know why
they say God in heaven and then you you
you have this picture of a guy with a
big white beard and he's he's up higher
than the airplanes go because you've
looked out the window in the airplane
and you know no I mean when you're a
child you think like that and I think
that stays with you I don't think you
ever outgrow that you you feel like oh
Buddha must be up up there somewhere uh
Buddha Paradise must be up there
somewhere and then the in heaven part
gets confusing right even in Buddhism
they say in the in the heaven or you
think it must be somewhere else right or
I don't know about you I don't know in
when I got to be a teenager I started to
perceive the world as uh what do they
call this
Russian uh
dolls what do you
call so it's a doll then a doll and a do
so then you start to see the world as
maybe there's Realms that I can't see
like onions layers and Buddhas are in
like the fourth layer out or something
like that but you still think think you
need a plane to get there or something
like that when you get more
sophisticated when someone teaches you
well then you have to realize your
Buddha Paradise will be right here
probably three jewels okay so you better
P it
in okay no I mean it it's just a pen
thing right what you saw is
normal and what you saw as a as a a room
in New York City you will see as a as a
paradise okay that's all you don't go
anywhere all
right
uh I like to think that in New York
there will be a lot of Buddha paradises
you know I think New York is a good
place for that I love New York I think I
think it will be a place like that there
will be many Buddha paradises in this in
this city this a special City special
people are attracted to this city and I
think it'll be nice okay anyway those
are the five qualities they don't
change now we get to the fourth body of
a Buddha okay this gets a little
weird K defines the Nea right the body
of
amination this
body when you become enlightened in the
second
millisecond your karma is so powerful
that bodies appear on countless planets
countless bodies appear I like to think
of it as a Michael Roach body appears on
every bus in every city on on the planet
like I'm I'm in a bus in goodat state
India and I'm on a bus in New York and
I'm on a bus in Hong
Kong helping the person next to me all
at the same time try to feel get the
feeling of that okay you are emanating
countless bodies on countless buses to
sit next to countless depressed people
and cheer them up you know if you're NBO
you're going to pull out a Snickers bar
you know like you want to share the
Snickers bar with me you know like he's
going to have all these Snickers Elation
bodies and uh like that just make people
happy okay try to imagine that try to
imagine what it would feel like to be on
to suddenly appear to get on of bus and
sit down next to every lonely person on
the planet at the same time okay cuz
that's what happens that's the emanation
body how do they Define it technically
in the
scriptures it's uh any body that you
send out which is not the one with the
five
certainties that so that kind of covers
it but I think it's kind of cheating to
Define it that way but it's not bad
right by the way at that point you have
the capacity to emanate bodies which are
not living creatures you can emanate as
a
tree for a person who needs a cool quiet
place to sit under and you can emanate
as the sound of the waves for a person
on the beach okay and you can sing to
the people from nature okay you are
nature you can emulate as nature and you
can sing to them from the sea and you
can sing the sound of the waves to
people sitting on the beach okay if it
would make them happy okay it's very
beautiful right so that would be
wonderful right to do that on countless
planets at the same
[Music]
time that's all we have like 10 minutes
let's sa the five wisdoms okay it's like
in Buddhism you're not allowed to
prostrate at the end of a class if
you're if you're going to not be with
the teacher in the next few days like
that and then there's something left
undone and then there's a reason to get
back together there's a
something what do you call it unfinished
work together so it would take about two
hours to do the five wisdom let's save
them
uh as a good luck that we have to meet
again and do the five wisdom together
okay so I promise to come back and do
the five wisdoms
okay
Thursdays uh we'll see I don't I think
I'm pretty much mhed up but
um let's do this from time to time I
like it and uh we'll do this from time
to time like smaller groups and uh
and then we'll do a couple we I owe you
the rest of uh ch right we're getting
into the secret part so I was kind of
holding
out but maybe we'll next time I come uh
to New York what is that oh she's trying
to get me through okay
um we'll we'll keep and the karmas that
create them it's at the 8th chapter of
the Alis Anar we had to memorize it in
the monastery it's very beautiful
because the whole text of my TR goes at
a certain Rhythm and then when you hit
the 112 qualities it goes into a chaotic
Rhythm it goes into a psychedelic Rhythm
it's it's very striking you recite for
like half an hour and then suddenly it's
going and it all goes off into some
enlightened Rhythm and it's very
beautiful